J. Robert Oppenheimer Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
J. Robert Oppenheimer Papers 1799-1980 (bulk 1947-1967)
MSS35188
Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967
76,450 items
301 containers plus 2 classified
120.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Physicist and director of the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey. Correspondence, memoranda, speeches, lectures, writings, desk books, lectures, statements, scientific notes, and photographs chiefly comprising Oppenheimer's personal papers while director of the Institute for Advanced Study but reflecting only incidentally his administrative work there. Topics include theoretical physics, development of the atomic bomb, the relationship between government and science, nuclear energy, security, and national loyalty.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bethe, Hans A. (Hans Albrecht), 1906-2005--Correspondence.; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-1980--Correspondence.; Bloch, Felix, 1905-1983--Correspondence.; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962--Correspondence.; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962. Niels Bohr correspondence and memoranda.; Born, Max, 1882-1970--Correspondence.; Boyd, Julian P. (Julian Parks), 1903-1980--Correspondence.; Bush, Vannevar, 1890-1974--Correspondence.; Casals, Pablo, 1876-1973--Correspondence.; Cherniss, Harold F. (Harold Fredrik), 1904-1987--Correspondence.; Christy, Robert F., 1916-2012--Correspondence.; Cockcroft, John, Sir, 1897-1967--Correspondence.; Compton, Arthur Holly, 1892-1962--Correspondence.; Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978--Correspondence.; Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984--Correspondence.; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965--Correspondence.; Feis, Herbert, 1893-1972--Correspondence.; Fermi, Enrico, 1901-1954--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Garrison, Lloyd K. (Lloyd Kirkham), 1897-1991--Correspondence.; Groves, Leslie R., 1896-1970--Correspondence.; Harrison, Wallace K. (Wallace Kirkman), 1895-1981--Correspondence.; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975--Correspondence.; Kennan, George F. (George Frost), 1904-2005--Correspondence.; Kusaka, Shuichi, 1915-1947--Correspondence.; Lawrence, Ernest Orlando, 1901-1958--Correspondence.; Lee, T. D., 1926- --Correspondence.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982--Correspondence.; Manley, John Henry, 1907-1990--Correspondence.; Marks, Herbert S., 1907-1960--Correspondence.; Nabokov, Nicolas, 1903-1978--Correspondence.; Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967.; Pais, Abraham, 1918-2000--Correspondence.; Pauli, Wolfgang, 1900-1958--Correspondence.; Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994--Correspondence.; Peierls, Rudolf E. (Rudolf Ernst), 1907-1995--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970--Correspondence.; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965--Correspondence.; Schwinger, Julian, 1918-1994--Correspondence.; Segrè, Emilio--Correspondence.; Serber, R. (Robert)--Correspondence.; Szilard, Leo--Correspondence.; Teller, Edward, 1908-2003--Correspondence.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968--Correspondence.; Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008--Correspondence.; Yang, Chen Ning, 1922- --Correspondence.; Yukawa, Hideki, 1907-1981--Correspondence.
Organizations
Federation of American Scientists.; Institute for Advanced Study (Princeton, N.J.); Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory.; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); Twentieth Century Fund.; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.; Unesco.
Subjects
Atomic bomb.; Exchange of publications.; Humanitarianism.; Internal security--United States.; Loyalty.; Nuclear disarmament.; Nuclear energy--Research.; Nuclear energy.; Nuclear nonproliferation.; Nuclear physics.; Official secrets.; Science and international affairs.; Science and state.; Science Study and teaching.; Science--History--20th century.; Science--Moral and ethical aspects.; Science--Security measures.; Science--Social aspects.; Science--Societies, etc.; Security clearances--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Science.
Occupations
Educators.; Physicists.
Provenance
The papers of J. Robert Oppenheimer, physicist and director of the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, New Jersey, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Katherine Harrison Oppenheimer, in 1967. Supplementary papers were transferred to the Library by the Atomic Energy Commission in 1971. Additional material was given by Princeton University Library in 1973 and Richard G. Hewlett in 1977. Further additions were donated by Alice Kimball Smith, Charles Weiner, and Herbert W. Smith in 1981 and 1982, by R. Joseph Anderson in 1999, and the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton University in 2016.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Approximately sixty magnetic tapes, chiefly of Oppenheimer's speeches, have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. Of special note are three reels of conversation between Oppenheimer and Niels Bohr in 1958; three reels recorded at the Seven Springs Farm Conference which include Robert Lowell reading poetry from the Russian and addresses by Wallace K. Harrison, Robert Lowell, and Nicolas Nabokov; and three tapes of interviews relating to the Los Alamos project. Two short motion pictures, “Thirty Minutes With Oppenheimer” (NBC television) and Edward R. Murrow's “A Conversation With J. Robert Oppenheimer” (part of the “See It Now” series on CBS television) also have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. Glass slides of various graphs are now in the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the J. Robert Oppenheimer Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of J. Robert Oppenheimer are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified items.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1904, Apr. 22 Born, New York, N.Y.
1925 A.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1925 1926 Student, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, England
1927 Ph. D., University of Göttingen, Göttingen, Germany
1928 1929 Fellow, International Education Board,; Leiden University, Leiden, Netherlands, and University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland
1929 1947 Assistant professor, associate professor, and professor of physics at the University of California, Berkeley, and California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, Calif.
1940 Married Katherine Harrison
1943 1945 Director, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, Los Alamos, N. Mex.
1946 Member, Secretary of State's Committee on Atomic Energy
1946 1952 Chairman, General Advisory Committee to the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission
1946 1954 Member, Research and Development Board's Committee on Atomic Energy
1947 1966 Director and professor of physics, Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J.
1949 1955 Member, Board of Overseers of Harvard College
1954 Denied security clearance by the Personnel Security Board of the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission Published Science and the Common Understanding (New York: Simon and Schuster. 120 pp.)
1955 Published The Open Mind (New York: Simon and Schuster. 146 pp.)
1963 Received the Enrico Fermi Award
1967, Feb. 18 Died, Princeton, N.J.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Julius Robert Oppenheimer (1904-1967) span the years 1921 to 1980 with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1947-1967, the years during which Oppenheimer was director of the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, New Jersey. The collection comprises Oppenheimer's personal papers and relates only incidentally to his directorship of the institute. The papers consist chiefly of correspondence, desk books, printed copies of Oppenheimer's lectures, statements, and scientific notes, supplemented by memoranda, inventories, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
There was no major rearrangement of these papers; Oppenheimer's own filing arrangement and cross-reference system were used wherever possible. He once described the papers as a “hideously complete archive,” and they document the many facets of his career. The collection includes material on theoretical physics, the development of the atomic bomb, the relationship between government and science, the organization of research on atomic energy, control of atomic energy and its role in international affairs, security in scientific fields, secrecy, loyalty, disarmament, the education of scientists and international intellectual exchange, the moral responsibility of the scientist, the relationship between science and culture, and the public understanding of science.
Material in the collection prior to 1941 comprises two small groups of scientific papers consisting chiefly of reprints of Oppenheimer's early scientific writings with galley proofs, holograph manuscripts by associates, and miscellaneous notes. Correspondence containing scientific calculations was written by such prominent physicists as Hans A. Bethe,; Shuichi Kusaka,; Wolfgang Pauli,; Julian Schwinger, and Edward Teller. Oppenheimer's writings for the early years, during which he established his reputation as a theoretical physicist, is filed in the first section of the Speech, Lecture, and Writing File. An annotated list of these early writings is also included.
Documentation of Oppenheimer's wartime contributions, including his organization and direction of the Los Alamos project, is centered in the General Case File and the Government File and includes material from such figures as Hans A. Bethe,; Raymond T. Birge,; Vannevar Bush,; Arthur H. Compton,; James B. Conant,; Leslie R. Groves,; Ernest O. Lawrence,; John H. Manley,; Franklin D. Roosevelt,; Robert Serber, and John Wheeler. In the Government File Supplement is formerly classified material transferred to the Library from the Atomic Energy Commission chiefly concerning the technical and administrative problems of atomic development from 1941 to 1953. Scattered throughout the collection are letters of reminiscence and Oppenheimer's comments on histories of the Los Alamos project which reflect the spirit and friendships developed during that period.
At the end of World War II, during Oppenheimer's activities as one of the chief governmental advisers on atomic questions, he served on almost every committee, both civilian and military, that dealt with the problems of atomic energy. There is a considerable amount of correspondence documenting these activities, but little material pertaining to his chairmanship of the Atomic Energy Commission's General Advisory Committee and the Committee on Atomic Energy of the Research and Development Board. The gap in this documentation is covered in part by lists and correspondence in the Security Case File. The Membership File contains references to activities of such scientific organizations as the Federation of American Scientists, the National Academy of Sciences, and various associations of atomic scientists. These files also contain information on other professional organizations, including the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, and the reevaluation by universities of the growing role of science and government within their own operations.
The control of atomic energy and its role in international affairs is a major theme in these papers. Closely associated with these subjects is Niels Bohr, a Danish physicist, whose letters and memoranda to Felix Frankfurter filed under Frankfurter's name in the General Case File relate to the idea of an open world patterned after the community of scientists. This correspondence, given to Oppenheimer by Frankfurter, is supplemented by the many letters exchanged between Oppenheimer and Bohr, numerous notes, manuscript drafts, and biographical data amassed by Oppenheimer for his lectures on “ Neils Bohr and His Time.”
Oppenheimer's hearing before the Personnel Security Board of the Atomic Energy Commission drew worldwide attention and is documented in extraordinary detail. The Security Case File includes numerous drafts of biographical and autobiographical statements prepared by Oppenheimer and his wife, Katherine, for his defense. There are a few notes taken during the hearings as well as correspondence with his lawyers, Herbert Marks and Lloyd K. Garrison. Much of the correspondence, including letters from many prominent people, and various published articles reflect public attitudes. The documentation also includes voluminous newspaper clippings and printed transcripts of the proceedings.
Although there is no official material for Oppenheimer's directorship of the Institute for Advanced Study, the Personal File contains related items on his appointment and resignation and the various literary, historical, and legal studies conducted during his tenure. Letters in the General Case File between Oppenheimer and Julian Boyd,; Harold Cherniss,; Herbert Feis, and George Kennan delineate relationships within the academic community, and Oppenheimer's correspondence with his secretaries from 1948 to 1966 provides further insight on both the man and the institute.
Following the revocation of his security clearance in 1954, Oppenheimer traveled widely and lectured on physics and the interrelationship of science and culture. The Speech, Lecture, and Writing File reflects this activity with notes, drafts, and printed copies of his talks and an index of titles and places of delivery. The papers also document Oppenheimer's participation in the Seven Springs Farm Conference held at Mt. Kisco, New York, in 1963.
Oppenheimer planned to write a history of theoretical physics in the twentieth century, whose leading practitioners were virtually all among his principal correspondents. Prominent scientists not previously mentioned include Felix Bloch,; Max Born,; Robert F. Christy,; John D. Cockcroft,; Paul A. M. Dirac,; Enrico Fermi,; T. D. (Tsung Dao) Lee,; Abraham Pais,; R. E. Peierls,; Linus Pauling,; Emilio Segrè,; Leo Szilard,; Yang Chen Ning, and Hideki Yukawa.
The arts and humanities are also well represented in the collection. The General Case File contains folders of material from such persons as Pablo Casals,; T. S. Eliot,; Wallace K. Harrison,; Julian Huxley,; Archibald MacLeish,; Nicolas Nabokov,; Eleanor Roosevelt,; Bertrand Russell,; Albert Schweitzer, and Norman Thomas. The Membership File, particularly for the Twentieth Century Fund and UNESCO, reflects some of the international issues in the humanities with which Oppenheimer was involved.
Addition I primarily contains a small group of originals and copies of correspondence from Oppenheimer to family, friends, and professional colleagues. There are also miscellaneous files composed of printed and near-print matter, photographs, writings by others, and one reel of negative microfilm containing “A History of the Institute for Advanced Study, 1930-1950,” written by Beatrice M. Stern in 1964.
Addition II contains inventories of classified documents from the Department of the Navy, U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, Department of State, and the Research and Development Board. It also contains miscellaneous correspondence received from the general public.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in sixteen series:
Desk Books, 1945-1967
General Case File, 1799-1967
Invitation Correspondence, 1946-1967
Membership File, 1943-1967
Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945-1967
Government File, 1942-1954
Security Case File, 1953-1967
Personal File, 1932-1967
Speech, Lecture, and Writing File, 1926-1966
Miscellany, 1957-1959
Government File Supplement, 1941-1953
Addition I, 1921-1980
Addition II, 1947-1957
Classified, 1944-1954
Top Secret, 1944
Restricted Data, 1948
Container List
- Desk Books, 1945-1967 (Box 1-13)
  Appointment books with a few annotations and miscellaneous notes.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1947, Aug.-1948, Dec., (3 vols.) (Box 1)
  - 1949, Jan.-1950, June, (3 vols.) (Box 2)
  - 1950, Sept.-1951, Dec., (3 vols.) (Box 3)
  - 1952, Jan.-1953, June, (3 vols.) (Box 4)
  - 1953, July-1954, Dec., (3 vols.) (Box 5)
  - 1955, Jan.-1956, June, (3 vols.) (Box 6)
  - 1956, July-1957, Dec., (3 vols.) (Box 7)
  - 1958, Jan.-1959, June, (3 vols.) (Box 8)
  - 1959, July-1960, Dec., (3 vols.) (Box 9)
  - 1961, Jan.-1962, June, (3 vols.) (Box 10)
  - 1962, July-1963, Dec., (3 vols.) (Box 11)
  - 1964, July-1965, June, (3 vols.) (Box 12)
  - 1965, June-1966, Dec., (3 vols.) (Box 13)
  - 1967, Jan.-Feb.
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1945, undated
- General Case File, 1799-1967 (Box 14-79)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent, memoranda, unpublished manuscripts received, secretary's notes, clippings, photographs, reports, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic, name of person or organization, or type of material.
  - “A” miscellaneous, 1943-1967, (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Acheson, Dean, 1947-1963, (2 folders)
  - African studies, 1961
  - Alberto, Alvaro, 1946-1964 (Box 15)
  - Allen, Henry B., 1949
  - Allen, W. P., 1952
  - Allison, Samuel K., 1945-1953
  - Alphand, Hervé, 1959
  - Alsop, Joseph, 1948-1966
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1948-1957, (2 folders)
  - American Cancer Society, 1947-1948
  - American Institute of Architects, 1956-1957
  - American Institute of International Information, 1950
  - American Institute of Physics, 1948-1965
  - American Philosophical Society, 1960
  - American Psychological Association, 1948
  - Amrine, Michael, 1947-1965
  - Anderson, Clinton P., 1943-1963
  - Annals of Mathematics, 1948
  - Anshen, Ruth Nanda, 1946-1957
  - Araki, Gentare, 1948-1950
  - Argentina, 1966 (Box 16)
  - Arms control
    - General, 1960-1962
    - International Study Group, 1961
  - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1954-1965
  - Arneson, Gordon, 1945-1966
  - Arnowitt, Richard, 1945-1957
  - Ashworth, F. L., 1947-1948
  - Associated Universities, 1964
  - Astin, A. V., dismissal case, 1953
  - Atomic bomb, twentieth anniversary, 1965
  - Atomic Industrial Forum, 1953-1954
  - Atoms for Peace awards, 1956-1957
  - Aydelotte, Frank, 1945-1955
  - “Ba-Bo” miscellaneous, 1942-1967, (7 folders) (Box 17)
  - "Br-Bz" miscellaneous, 1945-1966, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - Bacher, Robert F.
    - Correspondence, 1942-1964, (2 folders)
    - Publications, 1947-1950
  - Bacteriological warfare controversy, 1952
  - Bagby, C. K., 1949
  - Bain, George W., 1949-1950 (Box 19)
  - Baldwin, Hanson W., 1949-1952
  - Barnard, Chester, 1946-1957
  - Barnes, George, 1954-1956
  - Barnes, Joseph, 1951-1963
  - Barnett, Lincoln, 1949-1966
  - Baruch, Bernard M., 1946-1963
  - Basic Systems, 1961-1962
  - Baudouin I, King of the Belgians, 1958-1959
  - Beckerley, James G., 1949
  - Beckler, David Z., 1950-1953
  - Belinfante, F. J., 1957-1962
  - Belsley, G. Lyle, 1947
  - Benjamin, W. A., Inc., 1961-1963
  - Berkner, Lloyd V., 1950-1954
  - Berle, Adolf A., 1950-1954
  - Bernstein, Jeremy, 1958-1967
  - Beskow, Bo, 1957-1961
  - Bethe, Hans A. (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1966, (2 folders)
    - Publications, 1950
  - Bhabha, H. J., 1946-1966
  - Biddle, Francis, 1949-1956
  - Birge, Raymond T., 1943-1966
  - Birmingham conference, Birmingham, England, 14-18 Sept. 1948
  - Black, Algernon, 1956-1966
  - Blackett, Joy, 1965
  - Blackett, Patrick M. S., 1946-1961
  - Bloch, Felix, 1942-1943
  - Boas, George, 1950-1963
  - Bohm, David, 1943-1966
  - Bohr, Aage and Marietta, 1948-1964
  - Bohr, Niels
    - Articles about, 1949-1963
    - Conferences, 1944-1963
    - Correspondence (Box 21)
      - Barnard, Chester, Rockefeller Foundation, 1948-1949
      - Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1945-1964
    - Frankfurter, Felix, and Bohr's papers that he gave to Oppenheimer, 1962
    - Institute for Theoretical Physics, University of Copenhagen, Denmark 1952-1967
    - Notes, 1948
    - Oppenheimer visit to Copenhagen, Denmark, 1963
    - Publicity, 1924-1964
    - Writings, 1923-1964 See also Classified, (2 folders)
  - Borden, William L., 1949-1953 (Box 22)
  - Boring, Edwin G., 1954-1960
  - Born, Max, 1948-1964
  - Born, Wolfgang, 1945-1957
  - Boskey, Bennett, 1950-1952
  - Boulon, Erva, 1958
  - Boyd, Julian P., 1949-1966
  - Boyd, William C., 1945-1959
  - Boyer, Marion W., 1950-1952
  - Boyko, H., 1958-1961
  - Bradbury, Norris E., 1945-1951
  - Bradley, Omar N., 1952-1957
  - Brazil, 1964-1965
  - Breit, Gregory, 1942-1963
  - Brennan, Donald G., 1961-1963
  - Brode, Robert B., 1948-1963 (Box 23)
  - Bromley, Dorothy Dunbar, 1949-1950
  - Bronk, Detlev W., 1949-1963
  - Brookhaven National Laboratory, Upton, N.Y., high energy book, 1964-1965
  - Brown, Charles F., 1948
  - Brueckner, Keith, 1949-1961
  - Bruner, Jerome S., 1953-1964
  - Buckley, Oliver E., 1948-1951, (2 folders)
  - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1963
  - Bundy, McGeorge, 1954-1964
  - Burchard, John E., 1954-1955
  - Burkhardt, Frederick, 1949-1950
  - Burnett, Robert M., 1959-1961
  - Bush, Robert R.
    - Correspondence, 1947-1963
    - Discussion group, 1958
  - Bush, Vannevar
    - Correspondence, 1942-1953
    - Publications and speeches, 1945-1952
  - “Ca-Co” miscellaneous, 1943-1966, (5 folders) (Box 24)
  - "Cp-Cz" miscellaeous, 1945-1965 (Box 25)
  - Calhoun, Edward, 1959
  - California, University of, various campuses
    - Conference on calculating machines, 1948
    - Cyclotron, undated
    - Group for Academic Freedom
      - Correspondence, 1950-1951
      - Publications, 1950-1964
    - Summer school, 1947-1949
  - Camus, Albert, 1965
  - Cantril, Hadley, 1949
  - CARE, 1949
  - Carlson, Franklin J., 1954-1963
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1950-1956
  - Carpenter, Donald F., 1948
  - Carroll, George A., 1949
  - Carroll, Herman F., 1953
  - Casals, Pablo, 1958-1960 (Box 26)
  - Cassidy, Marion, 1949-1954
  - Cavers, David, 1949-1953
  - Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, New York, N.Y., 1952
  - CERN (European Organization for Nuclear Research), 1959-1960
  - Chadwick, James, 1943-1967
  - Chagas, Carlos, 1956-1965
  - Chases, Sherret, 1949-1952
  - Cherniss, Harold, 1949-1965
  - Chevalier, Haakon, 1943-1954
  - Chicago, University of, Chicago, Ill.
    - Cosmic ray conference, 1950
    - Nuclear physics conference, 1951
    - Office of Naval Research, 1948
  - Childs, Marquis W., 1948-1963
  - Christy, Robert F., 1946-1965
  - Civil defense, 1950
  - Civil liberties, 1948
  - Clancy, Hazel G., 1947-1950
  - Clark, Grenville, 1943-1963
  - Cline, Barbara, 1960
  - Cockcroft, John, Sir, 1947-1959
  - Cohen, Benjamin, 1952
  - Cohen, Karl, 1948-1953
  - Colby, Walter F., 1954 (Box 27)
  - Collège de France, Paris, France, 1958-1959
  - Compton, Arthur H., 1941-1963
  - Compton, Karl T., 1945
  - Compton, Randolph, 1950
  - Comstock, Francis, 1950
  - Conant, James B.
    - Correspondence, 1942-1964, (2 folders)
    - Publications, 1947-1953
  - Condon, Edward U.
    - Correspondence, 1943-1967, (3 folders)
    - Loyalty probe, 1948-1954
  - Congress for Cultural Freedom (Box 28)
    - Basel, Switzerland, 1959
    - New York Times, 1966
  - Cooperative Forum, 1950-1959
  - Copenhagen, Denmark, visit, 1958
  - Corben, Herbert and Mulaika, 1945-1964
  - Corning Glass Works, 1951
  - Cornish, Edward and Robert, Spaceboard Game Co., 1950
  - Cornog, Robert, 1947-1949
  - Coryell, Charles D., 1945-1954
  - Cougnard, Jérôme, 1948